<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nature &amp; effects of the new-found well at Kinghorne: declared by William Barclay, Master of Artes and Doctour of Physicke, and written in a letter to my lord the Earle of Dumfermeling, and Chancellar of Scotland</title>
            <author>Barclay, William, 1570?-1630?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1405</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114925</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850146</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850146</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15332</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15332)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 823:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nature &amp; effects of the new-found well at Kinghorne: declared by William Barclay, Master of Artes and Doctour of Physicke, and written in a letter to my lord the Earle of Dumfermeling, and Chancellar of Scotland</title>
                  <author>Barclay, William, 1570?-1630?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andro Hart,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini 1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page on A3v. A1 is blank except for signature within frame; A2 contains, with caption title "To mine approoued friende Andro Hart.".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (-A8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mineral waters --  Scotland --  Kinghorn --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="author_to_the_printer">
            <pb facs="tcp:15332:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:15332:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <head>To mine approoued Friende <hi>Andro Hart.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ASTER HART,</hi> beeing at <hi>KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HORNE,</hi> bearing company to my deare and ſickly Nephew, who is come thither to craue helpe from this recently laureate Maſter Doctor, <hi>the new-found, much celebrated Well,</hi> I haue penned a little Diſcourſe, containing in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>To my Lord Chancellar,</hi> the Nature and Effectes of this Water. But I am wonderfully
<pb facs="tcp:15332:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->importuned, either writing or diting Copies of the ſame. For the which cauſe I ſende to you, as to a Common Father of Letters, the principall piece: that you maye giue it the Cogniſsance of your Characters, and a patent Paſport vnder the Seale of your Preſſe. So conſtrained to cut ſhort, by the clamour of Mariners calling to the Tide, I take my leaue at Leith this 8. of Auguſt, <hi>anno 1618.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate friende BARCLAY, Doct. Med.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15332:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <p>THE NATVRE &amp; EFFECTS OF THE NEW-FOVND WELL AT KINGHORNE: Declared by William Barclay, Maſter of Artes and Doctour of Phyſicke, AND Written in a Letter to my Lord the Earle of Dumfermeling, and Chancellar of Scotland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDJNB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by Andro Hart, ANNO DOMINI 1618.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15332:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15332:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <head>TO MY VERIE HONOVRABLE LORD, My Lord the Earle of <hi>Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermeling, and Chancellar of Scotland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Knowe how little leaſure the Affaires of this Kingdome doe afford to your L. and I know how large a Diſcourſe the Argument of this Letter doeth miniſter: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall not diſtract your L. buſied at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion; neither ſhall I extende this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb facs="tcp:15332:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->but according to your L. intelligent judgement I ſhall contriue an obſcure and intricate ſubject to a compendious narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>This latelie found, and newlie-knowne, too-too long vnknowne Well,
<q>Si fama didicit jam non mentiri.</q>
This Well is ſo blazed abroade, and our Phyſicians, not without cauſe, are ſo loath to open their mindes concerning the ſame, that I, imboldened both by your L. coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and Vnderſtanding, haue taken the hardineſſe to breake the yce, and ſhow to your L. ſo much as I can perceiue, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the cauſes and nature of this Water, and of the effects and vertues thereof, that the reſt of my more learned Collegues may bee encouraged to dye their exerciſed Quilles in this wholſome Liquour.</p>
            <p>IT is a mixed water by the continuall flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing thorow a Mettall, from whence it hath contracted a ſpirituall energie, and a certaine <hi>Mercuriall</hi> ſubtile ſubſtance: To be ſhort, The Mettall which hath commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated force and efficacie to this water, is
<pb facs="tcp:15332:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->Tinne. The reaſons of my conjectures are taken from three heads:
<list>
                  <item>1. From the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the water:</item>
                  <item>2. From the effectes thereof:</item>
                  <item>3. And from the adjacent circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</item>
               </list>
From the water it ſelfe are manie pregnant reaſons: As that the water being a compound, and mixed bodie, it carrieth no ſauour or taſte of anie thing, but of pure water; which argueth none other Mettall but Tinne: For anie other Minerall, or Semi-minerall, except Golde and Siluer, would bewray it ſelfe, by taſte or colour. But Golde it is not, neither is it Siluer, which I affirme by the effectes: For all Phyſicians, both <hi>Dogmatickes</hi> and <hi>Spagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rickes,</hi> receiue Golde and Siluer amongſt their cordiall Medicamentes, and not amongſt the Nephritickes: But this water is by experience Diureticke, and aſſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth euidentlie Nephriticke dolours, waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the vreteres, and the bladder: which effects the <hi>Paracelſians</hi> attribute to <hi>Saturne.</hi> I neede not to draw the conſequent which willingly folowes the premiſſes. More, this water being diſtilled, or exhaled, leaueth in the bottome of the Alimbecke a Salt
<pb facs="tcp:15332:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->vnſalt, that is, a matter white like Chymik ſalt, which is vnſauorie, and ſomewhat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to ſweete, much like to the matter which the Alchimiſtes drawe from Tinne, and call it <hi>Saccharum Saturni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe ſecondlie, from the effectes I prooue it to be Tinne, Becauſe the whole fornace of <hi>Paracelſe</hi> keepe as a great ſecret in their Philoſophicall extractions, That <hi>Saccharum Saturni,</hi> that is to ſaye, the ſalt of Tinne is the onelie ſpeciall thing to cure an vlcere in the kidneyes, becauſe it is diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticke, and ſo carrieth to the afflicted part, and then it is deterſiue and drying, which qualities doe cure an vlcere, and which qualities wee finde in this water.</p>
            <p>Laſtlie, from the adjacent circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wee reaſon this way: It is not vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that there ſhould bee Tinne in that part, becauſe it is a Mettall familiare, and domeſticke to this Yland, the beſt of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> being found in ENGLAND. And the channell of the water, in that clift of the Rocke where it floweth, hath participated of the tincture of Tinne, as appeareth to euerie one that beholdeth: The Rocke it
<pb facs="tcp:15332:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->ſelfe notwithſtanding being as it were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brodered, and peſſimented with white la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of cleare and chryſtalline ſtones.</p>
            <p>AS Towardes the effectes of this Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, There are two thinges to be ſaid, 1. What it might doe, beeing Phyſicallie vſed: 2. And what it hath done, beeing Vulgarlie abuſed. For the firſt I will ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, becauſe I am loath, at this time, to trouble your Lordſhip for the other.</p>
            <p>This water is experimented to bee ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie aperitiue, and ſerueth verie much for the waſhing away of Sande, beeing taken in ſuch quantitie as maketh a ſpeate: (Neither hath it beene founde that an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great quantitie of it hath done anie harme) And it bringeth downe little ſtones from the kidneyes, and expelleth them alſo from the bladder. Yet it is not tried to haue force to diminiſh or demoliſh a conformed and ſolidated ſtone in the bladder, albeit it hindereth the intollerable doloures of the pitiable grauels, and quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the burning heate of their water, and cauſeth them make water without painfull
<pb facs="tcp:15332:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->dropping. It is very deterſiue, for the which quality it louſeth the belly of ſome. It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo very drying, and in this reſpect it bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the belly of moſt part of Drinkers: as we remarke the ſame accidents fall out in the vſe of Milke: For the croudy part bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſome, and the ſerous or wheyiſh part louſeth others. Nowe joyning theſe two properties together, to deterge and to dry, it maketh a ſoueraigne remedie for all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall vlcers, alſo for this deterſiue quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, it is good for the ſight, becauſe it taketh away all clouds or blots, which effuſcate or dimme the <hi>Cornea tunica,</hi> and cauſeth the <hi>Species intentionales</hi> to paſſe more purelie &amp; clearelie to the <hi>humor chriſtallin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I adde thus much more, That there is not a more daintie Fairde for Ladies: no not <hi>Oleum talci,</hi> which is ſo curiouſlie euer ſought, and neuer found. It plaineth &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheth their faces, and taketh away all blots and furrowes, and leaueth no frumples in their Skinnes, with greater ſecuritie and honour, than the venomous <hi>Sublimatum,</hi> or <hi>Ceruſſa,</hi> which they ſo frequently abuſe, Becauſe this water hath the moſt ſpirituall
<pb facs="tcp:15332:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->operation of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> quinteſſenced from the Tinne: which I confirme by two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: The one is, becauſe it is ſudorifick, &amp; procureth ſweate in aboundance, beeing drunken ſome number of dayes conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently. The other is, becauſe the tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament of it is hote, albeit it bee actuallie colde. The heate appeareth, in that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth to the eyes firſt a ſmart, and next a great itch.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this is a ſoueraigne and vnicke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie for that diſeaſe in Women, which they neuer acknowledge to be a diſeaſe, while it bee almoſt paſt remedie: and more than a diſeaſe, when Phyſicians haue none helpe, but only ſorrow to heare their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and the regrate of their lamentable negligence. So ceaſing to proſecute this warſh matter of water, I will neuer ceaſe to continue</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your L. moſt humble and obedient ſeruitour</hi> BARCLAY, Doct. Med.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="missing_pages">
            <p> </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
